Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Project Records, 1936-1989; 1942-1962; Series IV
  - NJN: Swedish Playhouse, Helsinki, Finland: Photographs
    Eero Saarinen's role in his father's alteration and expansion of this theater, designed by Nicholas Benois and completed in 1866, began in 1935 when he started attending design presentations in Helsinki in Eliel's place. The presentations were made with Jarl Eklund, to whom Eliel had entrusted responsibility for the design.
    - Existing conditions before renovation, undated (Box 59, Folder 45)
    - Exteriors, undated (Box 59, Folder 46)
  - NJN: Technifax Corporation: graphics: finish samples, undated (Box 59, Folder 47)
  - NJN: Unfolding House: Photographs
    - Model, undated (Box 59, Folder 48)
    - Negative, undated (Box 59, Folder 49)
  - NJN: University of Chicago, Chicago, IL: Hospital: Building requirements; housing law, 1955, undated (Box 59, Folder 50)
  - NJN: University of Chicago, Chicago, IL: Intern Housing: Drawings: Architectural, area planning, building sketches, undated (Box 61)
    Other Finding Aids
    Drawings Inventory (Excel)
  - NJN: University of Chicago, Chicago, IL: Laboratory School: Correspondence; building program; notes, 1954-1956 (Box 59, Folder 51)
  - NJN: University of Chicago, Chicago, IL: Management Center
    - Industrial Relations Center brochures, 1953, undated (Box 62, Folder 52)
    - Traffic notes, undated (Box 62, Folder 53)
  - NJN: University of Chicago, Chicago, IL: Men's Dormitory: Brochure for unbuilt scheme, undated (Box 671, Folder 2)
  - NJN: University of Chicago: Unidentified elevations of existing conditions, undated (Box 680, Folder 126)
  - NJN: Washtenaw County, MI: Master Plan: Negatives and transparencies, 1946 (Box 62, Folder 54)
  - NJN: Wermuth, A.C. residence, Fort Wayne, IN: Photographs
    - Exteriors, 1941-1942 (Box 62, Folder 55)
    - Interiors, 1941-1942 (Box 62, Folder 56)
    - Plans, 1941-1942 (Box 62, Folder 57)
  - NJN: Willow Lodge: Photographs
    - Model: interior, 1943, undated (Box 62, Folder 58)
    - Negatives, undated (Box 62, Folder 59)
  - NJN: Yale University, New Haven, CT
    - Wright Hall: Bluestone floor specifications, 1959 (Box 62, Folder 60)
    - Yale Co-op: Graphics: Exterior door sign studies; logo sample; alphabet, undated (Box 62, Folder 61)
      - Graphics, exterior sign, 1962 (Box 674, Folder 59)
  - NJN: Unidentified alphabet, 1963 (Box 62, Folder 62)
  - NJN: Unidentified aerial photograph, undated (Folder 684H)
  - NJN: Unidentified model photograph, undated (Box 675, Folder 77)
  - Job 154: Kleinhans Music Hall, Buffalo, NY
    Buffalo merchant Edward Kleinhans and the Works Progress Administration commissioned and paid for this music hall located at The Circle, a public park designed by Frederick Law Olmsted and Calvert Vaux. The architects of record for the project were F. J. and W. A. Kidd, Architects; Eliel and Eero Saarinen were consulting architects and were hired after the client became disenchanted with the work of the Kidd office. Collaborating with Charles Eames and Ralph Rapson, the Saarinens designed a building incorporating a tripartite curvilinear plan. The flat-roofed red- and tan-dapple brick and sandstone building is composed of two semi-elliptical structures, one housing a 3,000-seat auditorium suitable for orchestral music and a smaller one containing an 800-seat theater, intended for chamber music, with flexible seating designed by Eero Saarinen and Charles Eames. Charles J. Potwin served as acoustical consultant.
    - Correspondence, 1955 (Box 62, Folder 63)
    - Drawings: Floor plans, undated (Box 63)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, 1940 (Box 62, Folder 64)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 62, Folder 65)
      - Floor plans and sections, undated (Box 62, Folder 66)
      - Interiors and furniture, undated (Box 62, Folder 67)
      - Model, undated (Box 62, Folder 68)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 62, Folder 69)
  - Job 4001: Tabernacle Church of Christ, Columbus, IN
    The Tabernacle Church of Christ marked the beginning of a close relationship between the Saarinens and the J. Irwin Miller family that would result in the Saarinens completing five buildings for the family. In collaboration with Charles Eames, Eero designed furniture, screens, railings, and light fixtures for the church's interiors. Eliel and Loja Saarinen designed a figurative tapestry, The Sermon on the Mount, for the sanctuary. E. D. Pierre and George Wright served as associate architects.
    - Clippings, 1942-1955 (Box 64, Folder 70)
    - Committee brochures, undated (Box 64, Folder 71)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1961 (Box 64, Folder 72)
    - Drawings: Architectural, structural, mechanical working drawings, undated (Box 65)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, 1940-1941 (Box 64, Folder 73)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 64, Folder 74)
      - Floor plans; site plan, undated (Box 64, Folder 75)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 64, Folder 76)
      - Models, undated (Box 64, Folder 77)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 64, Folder 78)
      - Renderings, undated (Box 64, Folder 79)
    - Slides, undated (Box 64, Folder 80)
    - Specifications: Architectural; electrical; plumbing, heating and air conditioning; bulletins, 1940-1941 (Box 64, Folder 81)
  - Job 4101: Berkshire Music Center [Tanglewood], Lenox, MA
    Serge Koussevitsky, the Russian-born conductor of the Boston Symphony Orchestra, hired Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen to design a master plan for an extensive music center to include a 6,000-seat music pavilion, an open-air theater, a school, and an inn. The Saarinens' design for the pavilion, known as the Tanglewood Shed, called for a fan-shaped structure, clad in wood, with a flat roof and a clear span in the interior. Before construction began, the symphony, seeking to save money, decided to incorporate interior columns, which caused the firm to quit the job. The symphony later hired a local architect, Joseph Franz, who followed the symphony's request. In most other respects, the pavilion reflected the Saarinens' scheme. The firm also designed a 1,200-seat structure intended for chamber music and opera, which nestled at the edge of the main field. In 1959, Eero Saarinen, working with the acoustical engineering firm Bolt, Beranek, and Newman, added an internal canopy of suspended triangular panels to the Tanglewood Shed, now called the Koussevitsky Shed.
    - Acoustics, 1959-1960 (Box 66, Folder 82)
    - Clippings, 1939, 1959 (Box 66, Folder 83)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1959-1960, undated (Box 66, Folder 84)
    - Drawings
      - Opera Concert Shed, Chamber Music Hall working drawings; miscellaneous additions and revisions, undated (Box 67)
      - Section, elevations, floor plans, trusses, undated (Box 677, Folder 104)
    - Photographs
      - Front entrance, 1949 (Box 66, Folder 85)
      - Models and plans, undated (Box 66, Folder 86)
      - Music Shed: exteriors, interiors, sketch, undated (Box 66, Folder 87)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 66, Folder 88)
      - Opera House Shed: exteriors, interiors, undated (Box 66, Folder 89)
      - Opera House Shed: section, floor plans, model, undated (Box 66, Folder 90)
    - Press releases and comments, 1959 (Box 66, Folder 91)
  - Job 4404: Des Moines Art Center/Edmundson Memorial Museum, Des Moines, IA
    In March 1945, Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen's design for this art center was approved by the Edmundson Memorial Foundation board of trustees. The building, which opened in June 1948, is U-shaped, clad in lannon limestone, and has overhanging flat roofs.
    - Clipping: "Art Center in Iowa," Architectural Forum, 1949 (Box 66, Folder 92)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1959 (Box 66, Folder 93)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural, structural, electrical [blueprints], working drawings and miscellaneous sketches, undated (Box 68)
      - Furniture plans and details, 1947 (Box 69–70)
      - Renderings, undated (Box 680, Folder 127)
      - Sections, elevations, plan, court pool details, undated (Folder 687B)
      - Oversize boards, undated (Box 108–110)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, undated (Box 66, Folder 94)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 66, Folder 95)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 66, Folder 96)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 66, Folder 97)
      - Plans; site plan, undated (Box 66, Folder 98)
    - Specifications, 1946 (Box 66, Folder 99)
  - Job 4409: Antioch College, Antioch, OH
    Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen's master plan for this college expansion called for the closure of some streets leading to the campus, as well as for the construction of a new library, a theater, and a fine arts building to the south of Antioch Hall, the campus's most imposing structure, and a dining hall and two residential quadrangles to the north. As depicted in perspective renderings, the new buildings were to be composed of interlocking rectangular blocks built of brick and glass. Though the college had engaged the Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen firm, Eero headed up the project, and minutes from the college's board of trustees meetings indicate that only he, not his father, attended. The only building proposed in the master plan to be completed is Hugh Taylor Birch Hall, which had been intended to form one side of a residential quadrangle marking the main campus's northern boundary. Birch-paneled bedrooms contain space-saving built-in furniture designed by Saarinen. Max G. Mercer served as the associate architect, Arton E. Yokon was the structural engineer, and Dan Kiley was the landscape architect.
    - Clippings, 1948, 1949, 1951 (Box 66, Folder 100)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1962 (Box 66, Folder 101)
    - Drawings: Architectural and structural, undated (Box 71)
    - Photographs
      - Master Plan study, undated (Box 66, Folder 102)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 66, Folder 103)
      - Proposed library building: renderings, undated (Box 66, Folder 104)
      - Proposed theater arts building; renderings, undated (Box 66, Folder 105)
      - South Group Women's Dormitory: Birch Hall
        - Construction, 1946-1947 (Box 66, Folder 106)
        - Exteriors; dedication, undated (Box 66, Folder 107)
        - Interiors, undated (Box 66, Folder 108)
    - Slides, undated (Box 66, Folder 109)
    - Specifications
      - General contract; architectural trades, 1945 (Box 72, Folder 110)
      - Heating, ventilating and plumbing; electric hydraulic elevator, 1945 (Box 72, Folder 111)
  - Job 4503-A: General Motors Technical Center, Warren, MI: Drawings: Styling Building, [See Job 4807 for project description.], undated (Box 73)
  - Jobs 4506-A, 4506-B, 4506-C, 5206, 5207, 5515, 5516: Drake University, Des Moines, IA: Campus master plan: Photographs
    In 1945, Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen prepared a master plan for Drake University and designed a pair of buildings dedicated to the departments of science and pharmacy, as well as a women's dormitory complex. Over a period of more than a decade, Eero further developed the campus plan and designed a Bible school and prayer chapel, another women's dormitory, and a three-story masonry-clad addition to Jewett Union. The master plan called for expanding the campus to the northwest with a collection of loosely defined quadrangles. In 1950, Harvey Ingham Hall of Science and Fitch Hall of Pharmacy, designed primarily by Eero Saarinen, were the first completed of the new buildings. Brooks-Borg Architects served as associate architects on the project.
    The women's residential complex, which includes a freestanding dining hall, occupies a hilly site and was designed to maintain many of its existing natural features, including a large number of mature trees. Inside, window embrasures are splayed to diffuse natural light entering the single- and double-occupancy rooms, where most of the furniture was built-in and designed by the Saarinen office. Stuart Davis was commissioned to create a thirty-three-foot-long mural, Alleé, for the dining hall. Severud, Elstad, Krueger were the complex's structural engineers and Hyde and Bobbio its mechanical engineers.
    Documentation for the Drake projects, especially the Women's Residence Hall and Dining Hall, is extensive. Job numbers for these projects overlap and pertain to different periods of the work. Researchers are advised to thoroughly search Series IV of this collection for related material. Job 4506-A pertains to the Campus Master Plan; Job 4506-B was the Harvey Ingham Hall of Science and Fitch Hall of Pharmacy; Jobs 4506-C and 5206 were assigned to the Women's Residence Hall and Dining Hall; additionally, Jobs 4506-B, 4506-C, 5206, 5207, and 5516 related to general project work; and Jobs 5207, 5515, and 5516 pertain to the Bible School, Prayer Chapel, and Campus Development.
    - Negatives, undated (Box 72, Folder 112)
    - Site plan; models, 1947-1950, undated (Box 72, Folder 113)
  - Job 4506-B: Drake University, Des Moines, IA.: Harvey Ingham Hall of Science and Fitch Hall of Pharmacy
    - Drawings
      - Design sketches, undated (Box 74)
      - Plans and details [Job 1904], 1947 March (Box 75–76)
    - Photographs
      - Construction, 1948-1949 (Box 72, Folder 114)
      - Exteriors, undated (Box 72, Folder 115)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 72, Folder 116)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 72, Folder 117)
      - Plans; sections, undated (Box 72, Folder 118)
      - Renderings; model, undated (Box 72, Folder 119)
    - Slides: Exteriors and interiors, 1962, undated (Box 72, Folder 120)
    - Specifications, 1946-1947 (Box 72, Folder 121)
  - Job 4506-C and 5206: Drake University, Des Moines, IA.: Women's Residence Hall and Dining Hall
    - Award submission, 1955 (Box 72, Folder 122)
    - Correspondence: St. Louis Lightning Protection Company, 1948 (Box 72, Folder 123)
    - Drawings
      - Furniture and appliance location sketches, undated (Box 674, Folder 60)
      - Miscellaneous and furniture sketches, undated (Box 77)
      - Room layouts, undated (Box 677, Folder 105)
      - Working drawings
        - Architectural, undated (Box 78)
        - Architectural record sepias, 1 November 1950 (Box 79)
        - Mechanical and electrical [blueprints], 31 January 1951 (Box 80)
        - Structural, undated (Box 81)
    - Interiors
      - Cost breakdowns, 1953 (Box 72, Folder 124)
      - Furnishings
        - Living rooms, undated (Box 72, Folder 125)
        - Social rooms, recreation rooms, and dining hall, undated (Box 72, Folder 126)
        - Student rooms and housemother apartments, undated (Box 82, Folder 127)
    - Photographs
      - Cafeteria mural by Stuart Davis, undated (Box 674, Folder 61)
      - Exterior, undated (Box 82, Folder 128)
        - Additional material (Box 671, Folder 3)
      - Exterior renderings, undated (Box 82, Folder 129)
      - Interiors, undated (Box 82, Folder 130)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 82, Folder 131)
      - Room interior models, undated (Box 82, Folder 132)
      - Site model, undated (Box 82, Folder 133)
      - Site plans; renderings; floor plans, undated (Box 82, Folder 134)
      - Wall section, undated (Box 82, Folder 135)
    - Specifications
      - Color schedule, 1953 (Box 82, Folder 136)
      - Electrical; refrigerators; plumbing, heating and ventilating, 1952 (Box 82, Folder 137)
      - General construction, 1939, 1951-1952 (Box 82, Folder 138)
  - Jobs 4506-B, 4506-C, 5206, 5207, 5516: Drake University, Des Moines, IA: General
    - Clippings, 1948-1956, undated (Box 83, Folder 139)
    - Correspondence: publicity and press, 1955, 1959-1962 (Box 83, Folder 140)
    - Slides
      - Finished exteriors and interiors, undated (Box 83, Folder 141)
      - Graphics and models, undated (Box 83, Folder 142)
  - Job C-4519: Houston Estate, Cathedral Hills, Philadelphia, PA
    - Drawings: General development plan, undated (Box 84)
    - Photographs
      - Negatives, 1946-1947 (Box 83, Folder 143)
      - Presentation brochure images, 1947 (Box 83, Folder 144)
      - Job E-4601 and NJN: Furniture
        Eero Saarinen and Charles Eames won first prizes in the Organic Design in Home Furnishings competition of 1940, sponsored by the Museum of Modern Art, for their upholstered molded-plywood living room chairs and for their simple straight-lined wood benches, cabinets, desks, and tables. The Grasshopper chair (1943-1946, discontinued 1965) was the result of experiments in sculptural forms for chairs that Saarinen undertook during World War II. Called Model 61 by its manufacturer, Knoll Associates, the chair features a pair of identical laminated-wood frames that were bent to form its legs and armrests and gave the chair its name because they resembled the hind legs of a grasshopper. Later, working with Florence Knoll's consent and adapting a wood-frame chair she had designed in 1945, Saarinen created the Model 71 armchair, which was introduced by Knoll in 1950.
        The Womb chair (1946-1948), manufactured by Knoll Associates, consists of a single foam-covered and upholstered reinforced-fiberglass shell supported on a bent tubular-steel frame. Early models of the chair were made by a shipbuilder in New Jersey who worked in fiberglass. The Pedestal series for Knoll Associates (1954-1957) consists of chairs and tables characterized by one-piece cast-metal bases that taper as they rise to meet molded-fiberglass chair shells or tabletops. Saarinen originally intended the chairs to be made of a single plastic material, but this proved to be technically impossible at the time. Instead, the chairs' metal bases and fiberglass seats are the same color (either black or white), so that, coupled with their continuous curving lines, each piece appears to be a single form.
        Furniture projects in this collection have been combined into one subseries, which includes materials about the Organic Design in Home Furnishings competition, the Grasshopper Chair, the Models 71, 72, and 73 chairs, the Womb series, and the Pedestal series. Documentation for all of these projects spans 1940-1961 and includes drawings, photographs, correspondence, sketches, advertisements, and brochures. Patent applications and related correspondence for Saarinen's furniture designs may be found in Series III.
        - Advertisements for Knoll furniture [photographs by Herbert Matter], undated (Box 83, Folder 145)
        - Brochure for Knoll armchair and invitation to reception, 1957, undated (Box 83, Folder 146)
        - Clippings
          - Furniture, general, 1954-1966, undated (Box 83, Folder 147)
          - Pedestal furniture, 1956-1960 (Box 83, Folder 148)
          - Side chair, 1949-1950, 1956 (Box 83, Folder 149)
          - Womb chair and settee, 1950-1961, undated (Box 83, Folder 150)
        - Correspondence
          - Knoll furniture, 1952-1961 (Box 83, Folder 151)
          - "Pedestal" patent infringement [Knoll v. Burke], 1957-1961 (Box 83, Folder 152 - 153)
          - Publicity and press, 1957-1959 (Box 83, Folder 154)
        - Drawings
          - Chair drawings, unnumbered, undated (Box 85)
          - Knoll Furniture Program, undated (Box 86)
          - Pedestal furniture, undated (Box 87)
          - Sketches and photostats of "Pedestal" furniture prototypes, undated (Box 83, Folder 155)
        - Photographs
          - Chair prototypes, undated (Box 83, Folder 156)
          - "Grasshopper" chair, undated (Box 83, Folder 157)
          - Knoll armchairs and settees, undated (Box 83, Folder 158)
          - Knoll side chairs, undated (Box 83, Folder 159)
          - Molded shell chair, undated (Box 83, Folder 160)
          - Negatives, 1948-1950, undated (Box 83, Folder 161)
          - "Organic Design" furniture for competition at the Museum of Modern Art, 1941 (Box 88, Folder 162)
          - "Organic Design" furniture for competition at the Museum of Modern Art: Heywood-Wakefield series, undated (Box 88, Folder 163)
          - "Pedestal" chair drawing, undated (Box 88, Folder 164)
          - "Pedestal" chairs and tables, undated (Box 88, Folder 165)
            - Pedestal table with place settings and chair in garden, undated (Box 679, Folder 122)
          - "Pedestal" chair prototype, undated (Box 88, Folder 166)
          - "Womb" chair, undated (Box 88, Folder 167)
        - Slides, undated (Box 88, Folder 168)
  - Job 4612-A: Stephens College, Columbia, MO [abandoned scheme]
    This Baptist-sponsored junior college for women hired Saarinen and Saarinen in 1946 to devise a master plan, including a quadrangle, a separate row of buildings, and a chapel. Shortly before his death in 1950, Eliel Saarinen made sketches for a proposed chapel; after Eliel's death, Eero Saarinen and Associates produced working drawings, but the project went unrealized until 1953 (see Job 5306).
    - Clippings, 1951 (Box 88, Folder 169)
    - Drawings
      - Architectural drawings, structural, mechanical, electrical tracings and master site plans, undated (Box 89)
      - Colored pencil sketch, undated (Box 682, Folder 139)
    - General Development Plan for the Stephens College Campus, presentation brochure, 1947 (Box 674, Folder 62)
    - Photographs
      - Negatives, undated (Box 88, Folder 170)
      - Renderings, sketches, floor plan, 1949-1950, undated (Box 88, Folder 171)
      - Site aerial views and typical campus architecture, undated (Box 671, Folder 4)
  - Job 4627: Detroit Civic Center, Detroit, MI
    The city of Detroit hired Saarinen, Swanson, and Saarinen to serve as consultants on this project for a forty-three-acre site along the Detroit River, for which they developed many schemes. (Eliel Saarinen had created concepts in 1924 and 1937-1938, which were not realized. Eero Saarinen worked with his father on the latter design.) All the new schemes called for the creation of a large landscaped riverfront plaza containing the Veterans' Memorial Building, flanked by a convention center and an auditorium, and separated from the rest of the city by a wall of new government office buildings. As shown in the final master plan, publicly released in March 1949 and published in Architectural Forum that April, the center, estimated to cost $50 million, included thirteen buildings and a band shell. Despite receiving approval from the city's planning commission, the design was not realized.
    - Clippings, undated (Box 88, Folder 172)
    - Drawings, undated (Box 90–91)
    - Photographs
      - Convention Hall: model and floor plans, 1948-1953, undated (Box 88, Folder 173)
      - Existing conditions, 1936, undated (Box 88, Folder 174)
      - Ford Auditorium: renderings and models, 1950, undated (Box 88, Folder 175)
      - Models, 1947-1950 (Box 88, Folder 176)
      - Negatives, undated (Box 88, Folder 177)
      - Renderings, 1947-1949 (Box 88, Folder 178)
      - Slides [graphics and model], 1955, undated (Box 88, Folder 179)
  - Jobs 4714, 4714-A, 4801, 4811, 5802: Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, St. Louis, MO
    Between 1947-1948, a local nonprofit corporation sponsored an open national design competition in two stages for the United States Jefferson National Expansion Memorial, to be located on the banks of the Mississippi River in St. Louis. The winning design would be recommended to the United States Department of the Interior. Saarinen and Associates won the competition, bringing Eero national reknown and launching his career as an independent architect. The main feature of the eighty-two-acre site he designed is the Gateway Arch. Issues arising from a railway line on the site delayed its realization for a decade. Saarinen oversaw preparations for construction, which did not begin until 1963, two years after his death, and was completed on October 28, 1965.